It felt like a Wix ad was on every YouTube video.
Wix was one of the biggest website builders,
so big they’ve run many superbowl ads.
But now it’s dying.
Their value is down 90%.
From $19 billion, to about $2 billion.
And now, they’re being investigated for
potentially misleading investors.
What happened to Wix?
Wix has a pretty typical founder’s story.
Developers Avishai Abrahami, his brother Nadav,
and Giora Kaplan, were actually working on
a different business, when they noticed how
annoying and difficult it was to build a website.
But where there’s problems or frustration, there’s
often opportunity, if you provide a solution.
This sounds good, but it needs a tiny bit of
context.
Tension
Wix wasn’t first to website
building. Not by a mile.
There was already Squarespace, WordPress,
while GeoCities and Adobe Dreamweaver had
been around since the 90s. Weebly also
launched about the same time as Wix.
Though, Wix did have something going
for it. Specifically, three things.
For one, it was very customizable, which
goes back to the founder’s frustration.
Squarespace had better templates, but Wix gave you
more freedom, since it was drag and drop. If you
had an idea in your head, you could create it.
This made Wix pretty unique. Even if some other
platforms didn’t need coding, it was still
the easiest to jump into and start building.
But, ironically, this freedom
came with a very big downside.
It was built using Adobe Flash.
Not HTML like Dreamweaver or PHP like WordPress.
This allowed for more freedom,
but boy did Flash have downsides.
Flash had a lot of security vulnerabilities.
It had notably bad SEO.
On mobile, it drained battery, had
no touch support, and was unreliable.
It was so bad, that Steve Jobs refused to
let Flash websites run on the iPhone. He
even published an open letter criticizing it.
“Flash has been such a problem because the
way that it hooks into systems, it’s been a virus
nightmare on Windows, even on the Mac. And when
we got it running on iOS, the performance was just
abysmal and embarrassing and it could never get to
something which would be consumer value add.”
From 2012, Wix adopted HTML5, but still had
to support Flash for years,
because of preexisting users.
Though their “drag and drop”
model, was definitely a hit.
Squarespace followed suit in 2014,
adding their own drag and drop system.
But it sure wasn’t with Flash.
Wix was very much catered to your
small business owners, or individuals who just
wanted a website quickly. No coding background,
and little interest in it. The drag and
drop, naturally seems quite appealing.
Wix was freemium, so they preferred having lots
and lots of free users, with limited features,
who might upgrade to all the premium
features: Ecommerce, custom domains,
a business email, booking, more storage.
Wix was also pretty early to this trend.
And, they were very concerned
with “wowing” customers.
Wix catered to those who wanted something quick,
easy, and, most importantly: cheap.
“my SO is a freelance web design/build person The
types of clients she loses to Wix or Squarespace
are the worst clients. They want her to do a site
for $200, or for "the exposure... I'll let you put
your name on it!" They are the least profitable
and most fussy. Then she's got clients like the
local high-end interior decorator who is totally
fine paying $5k for a really nice, customized site
and then paying hourly for upkeep and updates.”
It feels like the best LLM
to use changes every month.
But even just a few AI plans can add up
very quickly, especially with tokens.
So… why not have them all
for one $10 subscription?
This is Mammouth which gives you access to
most of the latest, cutting edge AI models.
All for $10 a month.
Mammouth is based in Paris,
with their servers hosted in Germany,
which means they are fully GDPR compliant
They keep absolutely no training data.
But Mammouth is also the best way to use LLMs.
Their "re-prompting" feature lets you
compare models' responses in one click.
Click “reprompt”, and compare
responses between GPT, Claude,
Gemini, Grok, or any other.
Every LLM has its own strengths,
and Mammouth gives you the best of all of them.
It also comes with specialty AI features,
like Perplexity Deep research, image and
document analysis, or voice dictation from GPT.
But with Mammouth.AI, you don’t
need a giant pile of subscriptions.
One of my favorite features
are their custom mammoths.
Create different mammoths with their own
instructions, but also their own icons.
This plan also gives you access to Mammouth
API, which allows you to integrate models into
your own automation tools.
Or if you’re a developer,
put Mammouth code directly in your coding console,
like Windows Powershell, VS Code, Cursor, or more.
Mammouth equips over 400 companies and public
administrations with its dedicated plan.
It has great plans for both
individuals and companies.
Stay at the cutting edge of AI without
the lock in, and less of the cost.
Click the url in the description
and try Mammouth today.
Thank you to Mammouth for sponsoring our videos.
For now, Wix was growing fast.
In early 2010, they had 3.5 million users,
by around the same time in 2011,
that had jumped to 8.5 million.
And with that came funding.
$10 million in 2010, $40 million in 2011,
an IPO in 2013, raising another $127 million.
This website builder, now had a lot of cash.
And that meant, a lot of money for ads.
Though, some were much weirder than others.
This was Wix’s ad for the 2015 Super Bowl.
But they weren’t the only website brand there.
Each of these ads, 30-second
spots, cost $4.5 million.
These website builders were becoming more
than just SaaS tools. They were becoming
huge brands, with huge marketing budgets.
[Eric Mason, Wix, Director of US Marketing,
2015]: "We want people to understand who we
are as a household name and as a major brand"
Squarespace had the same idea:
[Anthony Casalena, Founder,
CEO of Squarespace]: the same year:
"We want people to have heard of us."
And weirdly, a bit of an arms
race began between these two.
Wix did the same again in 2016,
and even partnered with DreamWorks.
I can’t imagine how much this would’ve cost.
Then they did another in 2017, this one over
a minute, featuring Jason Statham.
It was working though.
This company was everywhere. It felt like
it was advertised on every YouTube video.
But not all of their marketing campaigns
were hits. Some, were huge misses,
and got them into a lot of drama.
But first we need some context.
Around this time, Wix ran into a bit of a problem.
In October 2016, Matt Mullenweg, co-founder of
the open source software WordPress,
publishes an open letter to Wix.
[Matt Mullenweg]: “Wix copied WordPress without
attribution, credit, or following the license. The
custom icons, the class names, even the bugs. You
can see the forked repositories on GitHub complete
with original commits from Alex and Maxime,
two developers on Automattic’s mobile team.
This blatant rip-off and code theft is beyond
anything I’ve seen before from a competitor.”
Wix’s CEO Abrahami, responds.
“Wow, dude I did not even know we
were fighting.” He argues the code isn’t stolen.
“ Here is a list of 224 projects on our public
GitHub page, and as you can see they are all
dated before your post. Yes, we did use the
WordPress open source library for a minor part
of the application (that is the concept of open
source right?), and everything we improved there
or modified, we submitted back as open source”
But Mullenweg wasn’t satisfied.
[Matt Mullenweg]:“Releasing other
open source projects doesn’t mean that
you can violate the license of the editor
code you distributed in your mobile apps.”
Ultimately, these two resolved this in private,
in person. So why does this matter?
Because, what makes this especially
weird… is that this wouldn’t be the
last feud Wix would have with WordPress.
In late 2020, Wix sent out a bunch of Bose
headphones to notable WordPress users.
But inside, was a QR code, signed from
WordPress, which linked to a video.
Unfortunately, I can’t find the video,
But it essentially had a “top secret”
video featuring a caricature of WordPress,
and potentially Mullenweg, acting
like a toxic, over-possessive ex.
Yeah, this didn’t go down well.
Not only was it in bad taste,
but it was also confusing. Some people
thought it was actually from WordPress.
Developers started to make fun of Wix.
“Wix is flushing money down the drain
with that Bose campaign. Such a waste of
money. They'll make a nice regift though.”
And some even made fun of their
broken web design on the video page.
Then Mullenweg got onboard, and
oh boy did it get so much worse,
when he pointed out Wix’s other
problems, like Wix’s lock-in.
“They’re like a roach motel where
you can check in but never check out.
Once you buy into their proprietary stack you’re
locked in, which even their support documentation
admits. So if we’re comparing website builders to
abusive relationships, Wix is one that locks you
in the basement and doesn’t let you leave.
I’m surprised consumer protection agencies
haven’t gone after them.”
He’s right though.
Wix very much wanted you to use only Wix,
even if they didn’t have what you needed.
But, it was about to get a whole lot worse.
If you’ve watched this far, consider subscribing!
You probably enjoy our stuff, and
it helps the channel too! Thanks.
Around this time, something else
was happening. The pandemic.
From January 2020 to August 2021, Wix
shares shot up 144%, peaking on February 19,
2021 at a $20B valuation. But you
can probably guess what’s coming.
The surge of pandemic growth,
eventually evaporated.
Q2 2021 was a $37.6M profit, but Q2 2022,
was a $111.2M net loss.
But it gets worse.
Remember Wix’s freemium model?
They had a lot of users. 222 million using their
tools. But, only 6 million were premium customers.
A conversion rate of 2.7%.
Wix’s stock was collapsing, in late 2022 it
was down 79% from peak, and down 54% that year.
So, they laid out a plan.
25% free cash flow margin by 2025.
To do so, they announced $150
million a year in cost cutting.
It was around this time that
activist investors had moved in.
But, surprisingly, this turnaround did work.
Wix was soon profitable. By 2024, the stock
had recovered, and a lot at that,
though not quite to pandemic peaks.
Their free cash flow margin in 2024 was 28%.
“Nearly double in 2024 compared to previous year”
Earlier than expected, and
above the original goal.
Q4 revenue was $460 million, up 14% as well.
This was great.
But soon after, the stock began to crash. Why?
Well Wix had a new problem. Perhaps the biggest
they had ever faced.
AI.
AI was, and still is, rapidly
changing the website industry.
Why pay for Wix to build a website, when
you can do it with the many AI tools? And,
do it faster with more customization.
The already saturated website maker market,
got a whole lot more competitive.
Wix needed to respond.
They bought Base44, a 6 month
old, vibe coding platform.
For $80 million.
Wix also promised some “transformative
products”, for spring and early fall 2025.
Wixel, an AI design platform to compete with
Canva and Adobe Express.
But more importantly:
Wix Harmony, an AI website builder.
But, Harmony was delayed. And,
when it finally did release, customers
found it was slow, and was missing features.
Product updates were also delayed.
The Wix Harmony ad in the Super Bowl wasn’t really
landing well. But not because it dealt with AI.
“This ad feels like it arrived a year late-maybe
two. The idea that AI can help you build a website
faster, easier, and with fewer technical skills
was compelling in 2024, still serviceable in
2025, but in 2026, it feels table stakes.”
Especially bad, since Squarespace also had a
Super Bowl ad, which was basically a cinematic,
horror short film, starring
Emma Stone. A very creative ad.
Wix, felt like it was falling
behind, on the race it had bet on.
Then, came the 2025 financial
results, which were… A bit concerning.
Their earnings and revenue were also below
expectations, and operating margins had declined.
Operating expenses had jumped 46%.
They also said “Expect free cash
flow margin in the low-to-mid-20%
range in 2026”. A decent step down.
Wix’s stock dropped another 27%, and
shortly after, came the investigations.
BFA is investigating whether Wix made false and
misleading statements to investors regarding
demand from professional designers, AI
competition, and its ability to deliver
new products and innovation to sustain growth.
“There had been delays in delivering product
updates and innovation to professional
developer customers, and as a result
the Company had fallen behind "the workflow
and the needs of" professional developers.”
Wix then announced major layoffs. 20% of
their total workforce, over 1,000 people.
Abrahami said this was due to “ fast evolution of
AI capabilities”, but, I’m not so sure about that.
I think the company is struggling, trying to
cut back costs, and is hiding it under “AI”
to make it seem as if they’re “putting more
money towards AI”, like other companies are.
Either way, the future looks rough for Wix.
Their market cap is down about 90%,
their business model is crumbling, and to
top it off, they also have a ton of debt.
Wix isn’t the only one feeling this pressure.
Another SaaS company that was all over YouTube,
and is now struggling, is Monday.com.
And like Wix, they may have
hidden the problems from investors…
Click here to learn the rest of the story.